SURAJ IYFR

DATA SCIENTIST

+31 6 81018048

suraj.iyer@vodafoneziggo.com

suraiiver.com

in / surajiyernl



/ surajiyer

SUMMARY

I am a Data Scientist by educational background. 2 years of experience in the telecommunications industry performing statistical analysis, predictive modeling, text analysis and deep learning. Have hands-on experience with managing stakeholders, storytelling recommendations, coaching a team on Python data analysis, productionizing models, and A/B testing.

EXPERIENCE

Customer Experience Analyst

VodafoneZiggo | Utrecht | Dec 2018 - Present

Deriving actionable insights and creating predictive models for customer experience improvement.

- Built and deployed a SparkML model to predict calls from traffic on the company website and proactively offer a chat instead to enable digital channel shift. Saves between ~750-2000 calls per week based on chat engagement rate. Improvements to the model are A/B tested.
- · Applied statistical analysis on signal data to understand effect of troubleshooting guides on modem signal and suggested recommendations.
- Performed Regression analysis on NPS surveys to inform journey managers on where to focus improvement efforts.
- · Applied text analysis on agent logs to determine more specific call reasons, trending topics over time.
- Pretrained Google's BERT on B2C customer service chat data and applied towards company-domain specific keyphrase
- Coached my team on Python based analysis, regression modeling, text analysis.

keywords: Python, Spark, SQL, ML, NLP, Statistics, LightGBM, Jupyter Notebooks, Qlik

Data Science Intern

ING Bank | Amsterdam | Sep 2017 - Sep 2018

- Graduation Thesis: Research and design of novel framework for predicting channel preference of customers to increase conversions and return-on-investment on marketing campaigns.
 - Translated business requirements of database marketeers into model design.
 - Formatted, cleaned, combined and filtered billions of rows of customer channel interactions data.
 - Engineered >50 features to quantify customer behavior across online and offline channels.
 - Implemented a production-ready three-stage ML framework to increase customer responses.
 - Promoted the product to business stakeholders.
- Internship project: Design of new banking leads generation model to improve leads quality.
 - Discovered and fixed critical issues in feature generation process in existing deployment.
 - · Leveraged feedback loop data and created a production-ready model to improve precision of predicted leads.
 - · Created a model workflow simulation to give proof of continuous improvement to stakeholders.
 - Forked, improved and deployed a python library to distribute scikit grid searches over spark nodes minimizing training time.

keywords: Python, Spark, Bash, Hadoop / Hive, Netezza SQL, Git

Research associate

Blue Mango | Eindhoven | Sep 2015 - Sep 2016

Researched algorithms to improve predictions of Ad Click-through rates (CTR) central to the online marketing business of Blue Mango.

- Solved the main challenge of class imbalance due to low CTR in advertising domain.
- Benchmarked multiple algorithms with and without applying SMOTE upsampling techniques.
- Achieved 59% decrease in average log-loss from 0.68 to 0.28 on real-world datasets with SMOTE + random under-sampling, thereby confirming research hypothesis.

keywords: Python, R, MySQL, Git

EDUCATION

MSc. Computer Science Engineering

Eindhoven University of Technology | 2016 - 2018 | GPA: 8.1 / 10

- Specialization in Data science and Software Engineering.
- Excelled in machine learning and data science coursework.

BSc. Computer Science Engineering

Eindhoven University of Technology | 2013 - 2016 | GPA: 7.9 / 10

- Bachelor Thesis: developed a web application to connect football coaches and players for organizing club activities. Achieved a 9.5 (of 10) with recognition for problem solving skills and team work under Agile setting.
- Specialization in Software Engineering and electives in Al and statistics.
- Well-versed in Agile scrum practice.

topic-analysis Aug 2020 - Present

Library to gain fast insights from text data with topic analysis and visualize trending topics.

- Extract noun phrases with POS tags, vectorize with BNgrams, cluster phrases based on mutual information into topics and assign documents to topics.
- Visualize trends of generated topics over time.
- · Based on the paper: Mining newsworthy topics from social media

spacycaKE Jul 2020 - Jul 2020

Simple keyphrase extraction extensions and pipeline components for spaCy.

- Based on the paper: Simple Unsupervised Keyphrase Extraction using Sentence Embedding
- Link to implementation: https://github.com/surajiyer/spacycaKE

spacybert Jul 2020 - Jul 2020

BERT inference for spaCy with custom extension attributes

- Provides a simple spacy compatible interface for extracting sentence embeddings from BERT model(s) for downstream application. Uses the Hugging Face Transformers library as backend for loading Bert models.
- Link to implementation: https://github.com/surajiyer/spacybert

python-data-utils Jan 2019 - Present

Utility functions and classes for many common data science libraries.

- A collection of standard implementations of common algorithms and helper functions used in Data science workflows.
- Link to implementation: https://github.com/surajiyer/python-data-utils

adidas Hackathon 2018 Jun 2018 - Jun 2018

Personalizing & improving next-generation shopping experience by integrating machine learning.

- Developed generative adversarial networks (GANs) to create personalized products by "transferring the style" of your favorite patterns / textures / images.
- Developed an independent hybrid mobile application with IONIC framework which communicated with the prediction backend, bringing our team to the finals.
- Link to implementation: https://github.com/surajiyer/Adidas-Hackathon-2018

keywords: Python, Tensorflow, IONIC, MEAN stack, Git

Recommender Systems Mar 2018 - May 2018

Tutorials on applying neural networks to information retrieval challenges.

- Using CBoW and Skipgram models to generate word embeddings for analogy detection and sentence reconstruction.
- Generate image neural codes using AutoEncoders and apply them to image retrieval.
- Using Siamese networks and RNNs to generate image and document embeddings respectively and apply them to one-shot learning tasks.
- Exercise on using Triplet network for unsupervised image-caption retrieval problem.
- Link to IPython notebooks: https://github.com/surajiyer/Recommender-Systems

keywords: Python, Keras, Matplotlib

Transfer learning with TrAdaBoost

Jan 2018 - Jan 2018

Developed a python scikit-learn implementation of the TrAdaBoost algorithm from ICML '07 "Boosting for Transfer Learning".

- Exploring transfer learning as a solution to sample selection bias correction in training models on financial datasets.
- Link to implementation: https://github.com/surajiyer/Transfer-learning-with-TrAdaBoost
- Link to the paper: http://www.machinelearning.org/proceedings/icml2007/papers/72.pdf

keywords: Python, Sklearn

Brexit Rumor Analysis Sep 2016 - Nov 2016

Rumor detection and verification system for the Brexit referendum topic.

- Setting up data collection and text preprocessing for >1 million brexit tweets.
- Engineered 30+ tweet-level, user-level and rumor-level features per tweet.
- · Helped with hierarchical clustering of tweets into predefined rumor topics using topic filters.
- Designed two models: (1) for verification of rumor, (2) for falsification of rumor. Combine them both using natural cut-off values to control precision and recall.
- Link to implementation: https://github.com/mthaak/2imw15-project

keywords: Python, Sklearn, ElasticSearch

SKILLS

PROGRAMMING **TOOLS & LIBRARIES** CORF SKILLS SOFT SKILLS Pvthon Bash Matplotlib Machine Learning Storytelling SQL Git Statsmodel Statistical Analysis Project Leadership NoSOL Text Analysis Managing stakeholders Spark Keras Software Engineering R **Pandas** Node.is Numpy Research LANGUAGE Java HTML / CSS / JS English Pytorch Professional Scikit-learn Dutch Elementary